In this country we had a struggle of freedom. I was a part and parcel of that.
इस देश में हमारा स्वतंत्रता के लिए संघर्ष हुआ था। मैं उसका एक अहम हिस्सा थी।
My parents were part and parcel of that. They were rich people, quite rich, I should say,
मेरे माता-पिता उसी का अहम हिस्सा थे। वे धनी लोग थे, काफी धनी थे, मुझे कहना चाहिए,
from every standard. You'll be amazed, My father burnt all his suits. They were
प्रत्येक मानक से। आप हैरान रह जाएंगे, मेरे पिता ने अपने सारे सूट जला दिए। उनकी
stitched in England. My mother burnt all her saris. They used to spin their own
सिलाई इंग्लैंड में हुई थी। मेरी माँ ने अपनी सब साड़ियाँ जला दीं। वे अपने
clothes and wear them. I had only one coat throughout My education, when I was in Lahore,
कपड़े स्वयं कातकर पहनते थे। मेरे पास केवल एक कोट था अपनी पूरी शिक्षा के दौरान, जब मैं लाहौर में थी,
which is terribly cold, sometimes can be like London. But we never grudged and
जो बहुत ठंडा होता है, कभी-कभी लंदन की तरह हो सकता है। पर हमने कभी असंतोष नहीं दिखाया
never grumbled and never said that, "Our father should have looked after us and done
न कभी बड़बड़ाये और कभी नहीं कहा कि, "हमारे पिता को हमारी देखभाल करनी चाहिए थी और
something. Why did he just sacrifice everything for the country?" Never, never, never.
कुछ करना चाहिए था। उन्होंने अपना सब कुछ देश के लिए क्यों कुर्बान कर दिया?" कभी नहीं, कभी नहीं, कभी नहीं।
That quality was created, I should say, by Mahatma Gandhi. He made everybody so
उस गुण का निर्माण किया गया, मुझे कहना चाहिए, महात्मा गांधी द्वारा। उन्होंने सभी को ऐसा बनाया,
transformed into a new personality. All the money that we had, everything that we had,
एक नए व्यक्तित्व में बदल दिया। सारा पैसा जो हमारे पास था, जो कुछ भी हमारे पास था,
all conveniences, all housing, everything was given up, not only by My father but
सभी सुविधाएं, सारे आवास, सब कुछ का त्याग कर दिया गया था, न केवल मेरे पिता द्वारा बल्कि
so many of them otherwise we could not have got our freedom. To get our freedom
बहुत लोगों द्वारा अन्यथा हमें हमारी आजादी नहीं मिल सकती थी। अपनी स्वतंत्रता पाने के लिए
this country has sacrificed so much. I must say, Gandhiji had a special charm.
इस देश ने बहुत त्याग किया है। मुझे कहना होगा, गांधीजी में एक विशेष आकर्षण था।
I don't know how he managed. He was like 'Touch of Midas', touched anybody, he became transformed, you see.
मुझे नहीं पता कि वह कैसे संचालन करते थे।  आप देखिए वह पारस('टच ऑफ मिडास') की तरह थे, जिस को भी छुआ, वह रूपांतरित हो गया।
And he was an extremely strict man - very kind to Me, to children - but he was an
और वह एक अत्यंत सख्त आदमी थे - मुझ पर बहुत दयालु तथा बच्चों के लिए - लेकिन वह एक
extremely, extremely strict man. He would not tolerate any nonsense at all.
अत्यंत, अत्यंत सख्त आदमी थे। वह किसी भी तरह की बकवास बर्दाश्त नहीं करते थे।
Throughout, if you study the way all these people were brought up, not only for freedom
पूर्णतया अगर आप इन सबका अध्ययन करें, कि इन लोगों का पालन-पोषण कैसे हुआ, केवल स्वाधीनता के लिए ही नहीं,
of or independence but even before that for spiritual life, anywhere, there's one thing
या स्वतंत्रता के लिए लेकिन उससे पहले भी आध्यात्मिक जीवन, कहीं भी, एक बात
very common, is sacrifice and the consciousness that you are doing
बहुत सामान्य है, वह बलिदान है और चेतना या जागरूकता कि आप कर रहे हैं
something great, consciouness that you are part and parcel of the Whole.
कुछ महान, चेतना कि आप संपूर्ण का अभिन्न अंग हैं।
People: [Long live Mahatma Gandhi, Long live Mahatma Gandhi, Long live Mahatma Gandhi]
लोग: [महात्मा गांधी की जय, महात्मा गांधी की जय, महात्मा गांधी की जय]
[People shouting slogans]
[नारे लगाते लोग]
I've seen it with My own eyes such people in this country, whom you may call legendary
मैंने अपनी आँखों से देखें हैं, इस देश में ऐसे लोग, जिन्हें आप प्रसिद्ध या काल्पनिक कह सकते हैं
but I've seen it. Thousands of people were killed and butchered. Children died -
लेकिन मैंने इन्हें  देखा है। हजारों लोगों को मार डाला और क़त्ल कर दिया गया। बच्चों की मौत हो गई -
nobody shed tears, nobody shed tears. Now, after that we are here to get our freedom,
किसी ने आंसू नहीं बहाए, किसी ने आंसू नहीं बहाए। अब, उसके बाद हम यहाँ अपनी स्वतंत्रता पाने के लिए हैं,
to get the freedom for our Spirit, to make our Spirit free from our greed, lust,
अपनी आत्मा की स्वतंत्रता प्राप्त करने के लिए, अपनी आत्मा को लोभ, वासना से मुक्त करने के लिए,
from your anger, from our conditionings, from our terrible ego.
अपने क्रोध से, अपने संस्कारों से, अपने भयंकर अहंकार से।